So we finished exploit-exercises protostar a while ago.
这意味着我们对多年来二元开发的工作方式有了很好的基本了解。
ago.
如今的剥削不再那么容易了，你们中的一些人注意到了这一点，因为
you tried to copy the source code and compile it on their own modern linux machine.
所以我认为开始引进现代技术和利用
mitigations by revisiting some of the protostar challenges on a current ubuntu.
And see how far we get.
它们仍然是可利用的吗？
So let’s have a quick look at the very simple source code again.
There were these variables, a buffer and this modified integer which was set to 0.
然后有一个gets（）函数，它将一些输入读入缓冲区，然后
doesn’t have a way to check the length.
这样我们就可以完全填充缓冲区，甚至可以在缓冲区之外写入
adjacent memory.
The binary on the old protostar VM had the modified variable just after the buffer.
因此，如果写入的字节超过64个，则会重写修改变量的0值，从而
change the outcome of this if.
So let’s try this again on a modern system.
I’m using digitalocean to quickly spin up a new ubuntu linux machine and ssh into it.
Then I take the code and compile it.
Oh, new system.
So we also have to install gcc, the compiler.
Now it works.
You can already see that the compiler is warning us of the use of gets().
你看，犯这样的编程错误真的需要开发人员忽略
warnings like this.
它告诉我们，你不必再去了解其他地方的危险。
you right away.
So let’s see.
Let’s try to input a lot of characters and see if we can change the modified variable.
But it doesn’t seem to work.
The only thing we can get is a stack smashing detected error.
And the process is aborted.
That’s the first evidence that a bit more stuff is going on here.
So let’s look at the assembly code that the compiler produced.
First of all let’s check why we couldn’t overwrite the modified variable.
检测到的堆栈粉碎与此有关吗？
Mh kinda.
But let’s see.
You see this location on the stack is where the local variable modified is stored.
You can see that because the value 0 is moved to it, like in the C code.
这里是堆栈上的缓冲区，因为它的地址是
passed to gets.
Like in the C code.
所以当你看到这个，你会注意到，修改后的变量不在
the buffer anymore.
We can write as many characters as we want, but we will never overwrite modified.
您也可以尝试对C代码中的变量重新排序，但这对
assembler code either.
And that’s not a coincidence.
Buffers or arrays are risky compared to simple integer variables.
Buffers are prone to buffer overflows.
So the compiler made the decision to order the local variables in a particular way.
And it kinda has something to do with the stack smashing detected message.
您看到此消息是由于堆栈cookie、堆栈金丝雀或堆栈保护
overwritten.
那到底是什么？
Let’s open the compiled binary in a disassembler to have a better look at it.
If you are still learning about this stuff, assembler code always looks very intimidating.
But it’s all about recognizing and learning patterns.
One such pattern is here with the stack cookies.
Because when you reverse engineer a program, you can basically ignore a lot of stuff.
例如，这里和下面，都与堆栈cookie有关，所以它什么都没有。
to do with the functionality of the program.
如果您对这个函数的大致功能感兴趣，可以查找
called here, so there is a gets, so that is reading something.
Then a local variable is compared and then it prints a string with puts in either case.
So you already get a rough idea from that.
But we already know what it does, so whats up with the parts of the stack cookie.
在函数的开头，一个值从一个奇怪的位置移动，fs位于偏移十六进制
28, into the register rax.
And then that value is placed onto the stack.
在函数的末尾，在返回之前，再次从
the stack and then xored with this mysterious value in fs hex 28.
This is just a check if the two values are the same.
If they are equal the function is allowed to return.
如果检查失败，并且这些值不同，则会调用堆栈检查失败
and the program will never return.
And this makes sense right.
所以在开始的时候，一些未知的值被写到堆栈上，然后事情就发生了，
例如，gets（）调用可能溢出缓冲区，
And at the end the value on the stack is compared again to this mysterious value.
So if we had a buffer overflow that overwrote this stack cookie, this check would fail.
所以fs，或gs或其它段寄存器，是特殊寄存器，根据不同的用途
在32位或64位上，如果您在Windows或Linux上，并且如果您编写低级引导或
kernel ring 0 code or if you write userspace ring 3 programs.
And there is a lot of historical baggage with them.
And to be completely honest with you, I don’t fully understand it.
Maybe somebody in the comments can correct me and add some additional information.
So take this explanation with a grain of salt.
You can imagine the fs register to point to some memory.
从这个过程的角度来看，我们实际上并不知道它的意义所在。
to.
The kernel (I think) set up where it points to.
So the process doesn’t really care where it points to, it can just use it.
And it can then reference different values at certain offsets in that memory.
So for example the stack cookie is stored at offset hex 28.
And actually the location must be somewhere in the virtual memory of the process as well.
Let’s install the gdb enhancment peda really quick because it has a great memory find function.
我们可以通过在堆栈cookie处理例程和搜索中设置断点来测试这一点。
the process memory for this value.
And you can see it shows up in some kind of mapped memory.
And if you check the memory maps it is included here.
And that is really the location where fs points to.
Because for example we can now overwrite this value with hex 41, so capital AAAAAAA.
当我们继续输入大量数据时，我们将在
the stack with hex 414141.
当我们到达函数的末尾时，堆栈cookie值明显被覆盖了。
by us with 414141.
But we also just set by hand the original value of the stack cookie to 41414.
即使我们无法检查和查看fs指向的位置，CPU也知道
value is and will compare those two now.
And not suprisingly we continue to the return and get a segfault.
Instead of going to the stack_check_fail.
This means we actually have changed the original value of the stack cookie.
很酷啊？
但你看，这并不是一个绕道饼干，它对我们在这方面没有帮助
case and magically make it exploitable.
We are just playing around with it to understand it better.
And we know that the original stack cookie value is stored somewhere in memory.
所以这些饼干有确切的用途，但不是神奇的药能阻止
every exploit attempt.
但是现在您已经更好地了解了堆栈cookie的局限性，它们只是
堆栈上的一个值，该值放在函数的开头并进行比较。
to the original value before the function returns.
这意味着我们可以覆盖堆栈上的返回指针，但问题是，函数
will never return because the cookie is wrong.
如果在cookie之前堆栈上还有其他变量，它们可能都是静止的。
overwritten.
所以它实际上只是保护你不被击碎返回指针的经典
buffer overflow.
它只会停止函数窗体的返回，但可能不会停止由于
to things overwritten on the stack.
所以在我们的例子中，理论上，如果修改后的变量放在
缓冲区，我们仍然可以覆盖它，而不必写到覆盖为止。
the stack cookie.
但是编译器开发人员知道缓冲区溢出是一件很常见的事情，所以他们希望
buffers to be as close as possible to the stack cookie.
Which causes the modified and buffer variable to be reordered in this way.
The buffer is placed after the modified variable, closer to the cookie.
Darn it.
There is another interesting thing about stack cookies.
Let’s rerun the program and collect a few random cookies.
Do you notice something, they all start with a zero byte.
So this is the little endian format but in memory the bytes would look like this.
So that’s interesting.
为什么它们不将所有8个字节都用于随机值，而是将其中一个字节折衷为
be a static 0.
这难道不是让它更弱吗，因为现在你只需要野蛮变形，嗯，猜猜，7字节？
显然，有多种方法可以攻击堆栈cookie，它显然应该
not be guessable or bruteforcable, but 7 bytes is huuuuge number already.
So probably good enough.
但正如您所知，有很多方法可以从内存中泄漏值，例如使用格式
string exploits.
So you use that to leak a stack cookie value and then your overflow is trivial again.
But some overflows happen because of a strcpy.
And strings in C are zero terminated.
因此，即使您知道堆栈cookie，并且您有一个易受攻击的strcpy，也可以
never overwrite the cookie with the corerct value, because you cannot write a 0 byte.
Because a null byte marks the end of a string in c.
但在我们的示例中，使用gets（），根据手册页，您可以看到
only stops at a newline, so you could write 0 bytes with that.
So it’s a very clever choice to include a 0 byte in the cookie.
It’s an additional protection against strcpys, even if the cookie value is known.
但也许你现在问自己，32位怎么样？
是否还有一个字节用于空字节？
Let’s find out.
To compile a 32bit program on 64bit you have to install some other stuff.
And we can also quickly check if this is not exploitable.
And you can see that we also only get the stack smash protection error.
Ok.
So let’s extract some stack cookies here.
You can also see that a different segment register is used here on 32bit.
But same concept.
And who would have thought.
Also a 0 byte in it.
So this makes only 3 bytes of randomness.
16 million possible values.
&lt;painful noise&gt; mhmh That sounds a bit more scary.
16 million depending on the context where and how the program is run is not much.
Maybe in our case it might actually make it exploitable.
I mean the original protostar VM was also 32bit, so I think it’s fair game.
But to be fair, 64bit probably makes it unexploitable.
So the plan is clear.
我们编写了一个程序，随时调用这个32位版本的堆栈级别0，并发送一个
exploit string to it, which uses random cookie cookie values to bruteforce it.
在某个时刻，我们可能会幸运地猜到正确的cookie值，溢出返回值。
pointer and redirect code execution to the output, the if case, we want.
Well.
The plan sounds good.
If it were just this easy.
We will need a bit more time for this so let’s do it in another video.
But it’s a fun challenge, so you should try that too.